<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="27"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[Introduction to the RC building example. Modeling and analysis of the design example.
                                                    P. Fajfar and M. Kreslin
































                                                                                              (a)


































                                                                                             (b)


                 Figure 2.1.1 Floor plan of the building: (a) basement levels and (b) levels above 0. The X- and
                 Y-axes as well as the origin of the global coordinate system and the centre of mass (CM) are
                                                         marked














                                                           28]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[Introduction to the RC building example. Modeling and analysis of the design example.
                                                    P. Fajfar and M. Kreslin







































                                    Figure 2.1.2 Schematic cross-section of the building





               2.1.2 ACTIONS


               2.1.2.1 Seismic actions

               The seismic action is represented by the elastic response spectrum, Type 1 (M s  > 5.5, EN 1998-
               1/3.2.2.2(2)P) for soil B (EN 1998-1/Table 3.1). The reference peak ground acceleration amounts to
               a gR  = 0.25g. The values of the periods (T B , T C , T D ) and of the soil factor (S), which describe the shape
               of the elastic response spectrum, amount to T B  = 0.15s, T C  = 0.5 s, T D  = 2.0 s and S = 1.2 (EN 1998-
               1/Table 3.2). The building is classified  as importance class II (EN 1998-1/Table 4.3) and the
               corresponding  importance factor amounts to  J I  = 1.0 (EN 1998-1/4.2.5(5)P).  Therefore the peak
               ground acceleration is equal to the reference peak ground acceleration a g  = J I *a gR  = 0.25g. Using the
               equation in EN 1998-1/3.2.2.2 the elastic response spectrum was defined for 5% damping.
               For the design of the building the design response spectrum is used (i.e. elastic response spectrum
               reduced by the behaviour factor q). Determination of the behaviour factor q, which depends on the
               type of the structural system,  regularity  in elevation and plan, and ductility class, is described in
               Section  2.4. It amounts  to 3.0. The design spectrum for elastic analysis  was defined using
               expressions in EN 1998-1/3.2.2.5(4)P.  The elastic response spectrum and  the  design response
               spectrum (q = 3.0) are plotted in Figure 2.1.3.













                                                           29]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[Introduction to the RC building example. Modeling and analysis of the design example.
                                                    P. Fajfar and M. Kreslin


                      uncracked section were multiplied by factor 0.5. Also the torsional stiffness of the elements
                      has been reduced. Torsional stiffness of  the cracked section  was set equal to 10% of the
                      torsional stiffness of the uncracked section.

                  o   Infills are not considered in the model.
                  o   The accidental torsional effects are taken into account by means of torsional moments about
                      the vertical axis according to EN 1998/4.3.3.3.3 (see section 2.5.3)


















































                                               Figure 2.2.1 Structural model


               2.2.1.1 Effective widths of beams


               The effective widths of beams  b eff  were calculated according to EN 1992/5.3.2.1. Determined were
               two different widths for interior beams (BINT1 and BINT2, Fig 2.2.2) and two widths for exterior beams
               (BEXT1 and BEXT2 Fig. 2.2.2). A constant width was adopted over the whole span. In such a case
               the value of the b eff  applicable for the span should used (EN 1992/5.3.2.1(4)). The corresponding l o
               (distance between points of zero moment) amounts to 70% of the element length (EN 1992, Figure
               5.2). The values of the effective widths b eff  are shown in Fig. 2.2.2. They are rounded to 5 cm.











                                                           32]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[Introduction to the RC building example. Modeling and analysis of the design example.
                                                    P. Fajfar and M. Kreslin




































                                         Figure 2.2.2 Effective widths of the beams


               2.2.1.2 Modelling the peripheral walls

               The peripheral walls are modelled with line elements and a rigid beam at the top of each element.
               The rigid beams (denotation RB in ETABS) are modelled as rectangular cross section 0.5/0.5 m. A
               large value for the beam stiffness was obtained by multiplying all characteristics (area, shear area,
               moment of inertia, torsional constant) with  a factor of 100.  Eight fictitious columns in X direction
               (denotation WB1), four columns in Y direction (WB2) and four corner columns (WBCOR, see Figure
               2.2.3) are used for the modelling of peripheral walls. For each column, the area, the moment of inertia
               about the strong axis and the shear area in the direction of the strong axis are calculated as a part of
               the respective characteristic of the whole peripheral wall in the selected direction (WB1* in X direction,
               WB2* in Y direction). The cross sections of the walls are 30*0.3 m and 21*0.3 m in the case of WB1*
               and WB2*, respectively. The moment about the weak axis and the shear area in the direction of weak
               axes are determined using the effective width of the fictitious column. We arbitrarily assumed that the
               effective width for columns WB1 and WB2 amounts to 4 m, which is the same value as the width of
               the walls W1-W4 in the storeys above basement. The torsional stiffness of the columns is neglected.
               In the case of the column  WB1, the area, shear  area and moment of inertia about strong axes
               represent 1/5 of the values corresponding to the whole wall WB1*, whereas in the case of the column
               WB2, they amount to 1/3 of the values of the wall WB2*. For the corner columns (WBCOR), the area
               represents the sum of the proportional values of both walls (WB1* and WB2*), the shear area (A s,22 )
               and the moment of inertia about the axis 3 originates from the wall WB1*, whereas the shear area
               (A s,33 ) and the moment about  the axis 2 originate from the  wall WB2*.  Local  axes (2 and 3) of all
               columns are oriented in such a way, that the axis 2 coincides with the global axis X and the axis 3
               with the global axis Y.














                                                           33]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[Introduction to the RC building example. Modeling and analysis of the design example.
                                                    P. Fajfar and M. Kreslin
































                                        Figure 2.2.3 Modelling the peripheral walls




               2.3 Structural regularity



               Regularity of the structure (in elevation and in plan) influences the required structural model (planar or
               spatial), the required method of analysis and the value of the behaviour factor q (EN 1998-1/4.2.3.1).
               As shown in this section, the test structure can be categorized as being regular in elevation and in
               plan. A lot of work has to be done to check the criteria for regularity in plan (see section 2.3.1) and, in
               practice, a designer may wish to avoid this work by assuming that the structure is irregular in plan.
               (Ir)regularity in plan may  influence the magnitude of the seismic action (via the overstrength factor
               D u /D 1 ). In the case of the investigated building the overstrength factor does no apply and there is no
               difference between seismic actions for a plan-regular and plan-irregular building. The test structure is
               regular also in elevation, if we do not consider the irregularity due to basement. For a structure regular
               in plan and in elevation, the most simple approach can be applied, i.e.a planar model can be used
               and a lateral force method can be performed. Moreover, the reference value of the basic behaviour
               factor q 0  can be used (see EN 1998-1/Table 4.1). Nevertheless, in this report, the standard (i.e.
               spatial) model and the standard (i.e. modal response spectrum) analysis will be used.



               2.3.1 CRITERIA FOR REGULARITY IN PLAN


               In general, the regularity in plan can be checked when the structural model is defined. The criteria for
               regularity in plan are described in EN 1998-1 (4.2.3.2)

                  o   the slenderness of the building shall be not higher than 4 (O = L max /L min ),
                  o   the structural eccentricity shall be smaller than 30% of the torsional radius (e 0X d 0.30r X , e 0Y d
                      0.30r Y ) and
                  o   the torsional radius shall be larger than the radius of the gyration of the floor mass in plan
                      (r Xtl s , r Ytl s ).





                                                           34]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[Introduction to the RC building example. Modeling and analysis of the design example.
                                                    P. Fajfar and M. Kreslin


               six  modes would be  sufficient  to satisfy the  requirements in EN 1998-1/4.3.3.3(3) (the sum of the
               effective modal masses amounts to at least 90% of the total mass).

                Table 2.5.1 The elastic periods (T), the effective masses and the effective mass moments (M eff )

                                                   T       M eff,UX  M eff,UY  M eff,MZ
                                       Mode
                                                   (s)      (%)      (%)       (%)
                                         1        0.92     80.2       0.0      0.2
                                         2        0.68      0.0      76.3      0.0
                                         3        0.51      0.2       0.0      75.2
                                         4        0.22     15.0       0.0      0.2
                                         5        0.15      0.0      18.5      0.0
                                         6        0.12      0.2       0.0      17.6
                                                 6 M eff  =    95.7   94.7     93.1







































                                     Figure 2.5.1 Three fundamental modes of vibration



               2.5.3 ACCIDENTAL TORSIONAL EFFECTS


               The torsional effects were considered  by means of the torsional moments (M Xi  and  M Yi ) about the
               vertical axis according to  EN 1998-1/4.3.3.3.3. They are determined as a product of the horizontal
               forces in each horizontal direction (F Xi  and F Yi ) and the corresponding accidental eccentricity (e Xi  and
               e Yi ). The horizontal forces are obtained by the Lateral force method of analysis (see section 2.6.3).
               Accidental eccentricities are equal to 5% of the floor-dimensions (L Xi  and  L Yi , see Figure 2.1.1).
               Torsional moments as well as horizontal forces and accidental eccentricity are shown in Table 2.5.2.
               Only torsional moments above level 0 were considered in the analysis.




                                                           39]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[Specific rules for design and detailing of concrete buildings. Design for DCM and DC. Illustration of elements...
                                                   M.N. Fardis and G. Tsionis

               3.3 Geometry of foundation elements




               Figures 3.3.1 and 3.3.2 depict the layout of the foundation in plan and a vertical section of the building
               showing the foundation elements. Single footings with dimensions 2.0×2.0×0.8 (width×depth×height in
               meters) are used for columns C7 and C10, 1.8×1.8×0.8 for columns C8 and C9 and 2.0×1.5×0.8 for
               columns C12 to C15. A common footing with dimensions 4.0×5.0×1.0 is used for the two walls W3,
               W4 and an individual footing with dimensions 4.5×2.5×0.8 for wall W5. A strip footing with width 1.0 m
               and height 0.30 m is used for the perimeter walls. Instead of a system of two-way  tie-beams,
               horizontal connection  of the footings and the foundation strip  of the basement perimeter  walls is
               provided by a foundation slab cast right below the top of the footings and the perimeter foundation
               strip (see clause 5.4.1.2 para. (2), (3) and (7) of EN 1998-5:2004). This slab serves also as a floor of
               the lower basement and helps create a rigid-box foundation system together with the perimeter walls
               and the slab at the roof of the upper basement.



                      1               2               3               4              5               6

                A










                B

                                             SLAB







                C









                D

                                                           BASEMENT

                                             Fig. 3.3.1 Plan of the foundation

















                                                           56]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[Specific rules for design and detailing of concrete buildings. Design for DCM and DC. Illustration of elements...
                                                   M.N. Fardis and G. Tsionis

                                       D             C            B             A

































                                                       SCHEMATIC SECTION

                            Fig. 3.3.2 Section in the Y direction showing the foundation elements



               3.4 ULS  and  SLS  verifications  and  detailing  according  to

                      Eurocodes 8 and 2



               3.4.1 GENERAL



               Clause 4.4.2.1(1) of Eurocode 8 prescribes the conditions regarding resistance, ductility, equilibrium
               and foundation stability that should be met at the ultimate limit state. To  satisfy the resistance
               condition, it is verified that for all structural elements and all critical regions E d  ≤ R d , where E d  is the
               design value of the action effect due to the seismic design situation and  R d  is the corresponding
               design resistance of the element. In the resistance calculations, clause 5.2.4(2) recommends the use
               of the partial factors for material properties applicable for the persistent and transient design situations.
               According to clause 2.4.2.4(1) of Eurocode 2, their recommended values are γ c  = 1.5 for concrete and
               γ s  = 1.15 for reinforcing steel.


               3.4.2 OVERVIEW OF THE DETAILED DESIGN PROCEDURE


               Especially in frames, capacity design introduces strong interdependence between various phases of a
               building’s detailed seismic design for ductility, within or between members:
                      o  dimensioning a column in flexure depends on the amount and layout of the longitudinal
                          reinforcement of the beams it is connected to in any horizontal direction;
                      o  dimensioning of a column or a beam in shear depends on the amount and detailing of its
                          own longitudinal reinforcement, as well as of those framing into them at either end;




                                                           57]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[Specific rules for the design...: (iii).Composite steel concrete frame with eccentric and concentric bracings
                                                   H. Degee and A Plumier



               5.18 Definition of the structure




               5.18.1 DIMENSIONS, MATERIAL PROPERTIES AND EARTHQUAKE ACTION


               Dimensions


































                                        Fig. 5.18.1 3D view of the 5 storey building






















                 View of the building – X-direction – Eccentric   View of the  building – Y-direction – Concentric
                                 bracings                                     bracings
                                      Fig. 5.18.2 The office building and its bracings









                                                           191]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[3  6  5  4                                                                  Fig. 3.5.6 Beam framing plan at roof   70













                      2













                      1

                                                                                              Roof

                               A                           B                           C]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[6













                      5











                                                                                                  Fig. 3.5.6 Beam framing plan at roof
                      4






                                                                                                                  70





                      3













                      2













                      1

                                                                                              Roof
                               A                           B                           C]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[3  6  5  4                                                                  Fig. 3.5.7 Beam framing plan at storey 5   71













                    2













                    1
                                                                                           Level 5



                             A                           B                           C]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[6













                    5













                    4






                                                                                                Fig. 3.5.7 Beam framing plan at storey 5   71





                    3













                    2













                    1
                                                                                           Level 5


                             A                           B                           C]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[3  6  5  4                                                                  Fig. 3.5.8 Beam framing plan at storey 4   72













                    2













                    1
                                                                                           Level 4



                             A                           B                           C]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[6













                    5













                    4






                                                                                                Fig. 3.5.8 Beam framing plan at storey 4   72





                    3













                    2













                    1
                                                                                           Level 4


                             A                           B                           C]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[3  6  5  4                                                                  Fig. 3.5.9 Beam framing plan at storey 3   73













                    2













                    1
                                                                                           Level 3



                             A                           B                           C]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[6













                    5













                    4






                                                                                                Fig. 3.5.9 Beam framing plan at storey 3   73





                    3













                    2













                    1
                                                                                           Level 3


                             A                           B                           C]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[3  6  5  4                                                                  Fig. 3.5.10 Beam framing plan at storey 2      74













                    2













                    1
                                                                                            Level 2



                             A                           B                           C]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[6













                    5













                    4






                                                                                                Fig. 3.5.10 Beam framing plan at storey 2      74





                    3













                    2













                    1
                                                                                            Level 2



                             A                           B                           C]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[3  6  5  4                                                                  Fig. 3.5.11 Beam framing plan at storey 1   75













                    2













                    1
                                                                                            Level 1



                             A                           B                           C]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[6













                    5













                    4






                                                                                                Fig. 3.5.11 Beam framing plan at storey 1   75





                    3













                    2













                    1
                                                                                            Level 1


                             A                           B                           C]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[3  6  5  4                                                                         Beam framing plan at storey 0   76
                                                                                                        Fig. 3.5.12










                     2











                     1
                                                                                                  Level 0


                            A                     B                    C                     D]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[6










                     5






                                                                                                        Beam framing plan at storey 0



                     4





                                                                                                                  76




                     3
                                                                                                        Fig. 3.5.12










                     2











                     1
                                                                                                  Level 0


                            A                     B                    C                     D]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[3  6  5  4                                                                        Beam framing plan at storey -1   77
                                                                                                       Fig. 3.5.13










                     2










                     1
                                                                                                 Level -1


                            A                    B                     C                    D]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[6











                     5





                                                                                                       Beam framing plan at storey -1



                     4





                                                                                                                  77




                     3
                                                                                                       Fig. 3.5.13









                     2











                     1
                                                                                                 Level -1


                            A                    B                     C                    D]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[Fig. 3.5.14
                     3  6  5  4                                                                   BASEMENT  Reinforcement of footings   78



                                                        SLAB





                     2











                     1



                            A                     B                    C                     D]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[6











                     5







                                                                                                        Reinforcement of footings


                     4


                                                                                                  BASEMENT

                                                                                                                  78




                                                                                                        Fig. 3.5.14
                     3



                                                        SLAB





                     2











                     1



                            A                     B                    C                     D]]></page></pages></Search>